Guide to the Leland Starnes, Director of the Yale Dramatic Association, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Leland Starnes, director of the Yale Dramatic Association, records
1950-1968
RU 958
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
The records consist primarily of the production files maintained by Leland Starnes as director of the Yale Dramatic Association (Yale Dramat). Included are prompt scripts, notes, photographs, cast lists, rehearsal schedules, sheet music, budgets, ground plans, stage designs (sketches), programs, posters, sound recordings, and newsclippings. Also included are a complete set of meeting minutes of the Yale Dramatic Association from 1960 to 1968 and a small amount of correspondence.
Yale University. Dramatic Association
Starnes, Leland
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies and organizations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Mary Starnes, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession and chronologically by year of production therein.
Scope and Contents
The records are arranged in two accessions. The bulk of the records consist of production files maintained by Leland Starnes as director of the Yale Dramatic Association. The files offer a glimpse into the director's creative process through annotated prompt scripts, correspondence, and research notes, as well as to the productions themselves, through cast lists, programs, photographs, sound recordings and newsclippings.
Additional documention on Starnes' productions is included in the Yale Dramatic Association Records (RU 300) in Manuscripts and Archives.
Biographical / Historical
Leland Starnes received his B.A. (1950) and M.A.T. (1951) from Harvard University and his Doctor of Fine Arts from Yale University in 1965. In addition to being the director of the Yale Dramatic Association from 1960 to 1968, he was an instructor of speech (1960-1966) and assistant professor (1966-1967) in the Yale School of Drama. Starnes left Yale in 1968 to become Director of Drama at the University of Pittsburgh.
Biographical / Historical
The Yale Dramatic Association was established in 1900.
College students -- Societies, etc.; College theater; Theater programs; Theater; Theatrical posters, American; Theatrical producers and directors; Photographs; Playbills; Slides (photographs); Yale University -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Dramatic Association
- Records, 1960-1968; Accession 2004-A-181
  Scope and Contents
  The records are arranged under two headings: General and Production files, and by size and format. General records consist of programs for Yale Dramatic Association festivals and subscription flyers. The Production files, arranged chronologically, contain records documenting Leland Starnes' productions from 1960-1964. Items in the Posters, Folio, and Audiovisual sections are arranged chronologically, and cross references from the Production files have been provided. An itemized list of the material for each production (play) is available in the first file for the production.
  - General
    - Yale Dramatic festival and Yale Dramat programs, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Subscription flyers, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Production files
    - Camino Real, 1960 November
      - General (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Ground plan
        General note
        See: box 5
      - Newsclippings (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Photographs and slides (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Sound recordings
        See: boxes 6-8
    - Thieves' Carnival, 1961 February
      - General (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
      - Ground plans
      - Photographs and slides (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Sound recording
        See: box 9
    - Booth is Back in Town, 1961 May, June
      - General (Box 1, Folder 9 - 10)
      - Ground plans
      - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Sound recordings
        See: boxes 10-11
    - Henry VI, Part III, 1961 November
      - General (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Ground plans
      - Newsclippings (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Photographs and slides (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Arsenic and Old Lace, 1962 February
      - General (Box 1, Folder 15)
        See also: box 4
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Finian's Rainbow, 1962 Apr, June
      - General (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs and slides (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Caucasian Chalk Circle, 1962 November
      - General (Box 2, Folder 19 - 20)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Sound recording
        See: boxes 12-13
    - Playboy of the Western World, 1963 February
      - General (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Newsclippings (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Once Upon a Mattress, 1963 Apr, June
      - General (Box 2, Folder 25 - 26)
      - Ground plans
      - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Men without Shadows, 1963 November
      - General (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Sound recording
        See: box 14
    - The Good Soldier Schweik, 1964 February
      - General (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Sound recording
        See: box 15
    - The Taming of the Shrew, 1964 Apr, June
      - General (Box 3, Folder 32 - 33)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Richard III, 1964 November
      - General (Box 3, Folder 35 - 36)
      - Ground plans
      - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Sound recording
        See: boxes 15-18
    - Country Wife, 1965
      General
  - Posters (Box 4)
  - Folio (Box 5)
  - Audiovisual materials
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - Camino Real
      - Sound, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 6)
      - Music, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 7)
      - "Gunsmoke" Wind, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 8)
    - Thieves' Carnival, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
    - Booth is Back in Town
      - Piano, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
      - Yale Dramatic Association Presents Booth is Back in Town! A New Musical, phonodisc (LP) (Box 11)
    - Caucasian Chalk Circle
      - Saturday, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 12)
      - Tuesday, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 13)
    - Men Without Shadows, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 14)
    - The Good Soldier Schweik, Richard III, Country Wife, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 15)
    - Richard III
      - Tape A, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 16)
      - Tape B, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 17)
      - Music, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 18)
- Records, circa 1950s-1968; Accession 2004-A-204
  The records are arranged under two headings: General and Production files, and by size and format. General records consist of a small amount of correspondence and Yale Dramatic Association meeting minutes. The Production files, arranged chronologically, contain records documenting Leland Starnes productions from 1965 to 1968. Items in the Oversize, Folio, and Audiovisual sections are arranged chronologically, and cross references from the Production files have been provided. An itemized list of the material for each production (play) is available in the first file for the production. This accession also contains a few pre-1960 Dramatic Association posters.
  - General
    - Correspondence
      - Moscow Art Theatre, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Minutes of the Yale University Dramatic Association, 1960 May-1968 May (Box 1, Folder 3 - 6)
  - Production files
    - Breaking Point, 1965 February
      - General (Box 2, Folder 7 - 8)
        See also: box 5, folder 40
      - Ground plan
        See: box 6
      - Newsclippings (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Sound recording
        See: box 7
    - The Country Wife, 1965 Apr, June
      - General (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs and slides (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Death of Doctor Faust, 1965 November
      - General (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Ground plan
      - Newsclippings (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Photographs and slides (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Sound recording
        See: box 8
    - Mister Roberts, 1966 February
      - General (Box 2, Folder 16)
        See also: box 5, folder 41
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Threepenny Opera, 1966 Apr, June
      - General (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - The Shoemaker's Holiday, 1966 November
      - General (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Sound recordings
        See: boxes 9-11
    - Waiting for Godot, 1967 February
      - General (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Sound recording
        See: box 12
    - Hunger and Thirst, 1967 Apr, June
      - General (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Ground plan
      - Newsclippings (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - "Notes for a Production of Hunger and Thirst," by Leland Starnes (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Photographs and slides (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Research Material (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Sound recordings
        See: boxes 13-16
    - Dark of the Moon, 1967 November
      - General (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Ground plan
      - Newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Sound recordings
        See: boxes 17-19
    - Rhinoceros, 1968 February
      - General (Box 4, Folder 32 - 33)
      - Ground plan
      - Newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Sound recordings
        See: boxes 20-23
    - Twelfth Night, 1968 Apr, June
      - General (Box 4, Folder 36 - 37)
      - Ground plan
      - Photographs and Slides (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Oversize
    - Posters
      - Film Forum, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Fruits of Culture: A Social Satire, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Tom Jones, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Tamerlaine, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Breaking Point, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - The Country Wife, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - The Death of Doctor Faust, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Waiting for Godot, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Hunger and Thirst, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Sketches and notes
      - Shortt, Paul R. [for Mister Roberts], 1966 January (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Rasmussen, Tom [for Dark of the Moon], 1967 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Folio (Box 6)
  - Audiovisual materials
    - Breaking Point [reel-to-reel original tape; restricted], 1965 February (Box 7)
    - Death of Doctor Faust [reel-to-reel original tape; restricted], 1965 November (Box 8)
    - The Shoemaker's Holiday, 1966 November
      - Tape 1, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 9)
      - Tape 2, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 10)
      - Sound, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
    - Waiting for Godot [reel-to-reel original tape; restricted], 1967 February (Box 12)
    - Hunger and Thirst, 1967 Apr, June
      - Tape 1, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 13)
      - Tape 2, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 14)
      - Tape 3, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 15)
      - Tape 4, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 16)
    - Dark of the Moon, 1967 November
      - Tape 1, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 17)
      - Tape 2, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 18)
      - Tape 3, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 19)
    - Rhinoceros, 1968 February
      - Tape A, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 20)
      - Tape B, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 21)
      - Tape C, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 22)
      - Tape D, audiotape (reel-to-reel) (Box 23)